本节我想为大家展示在实际中RSA是如何使用的
In this segment I wanna show you how RSA
is used in practice and in particular, I
特别地，我想告诉大家一个标准，叫做公钥密码学一号标准
wanna tell you about a standard called a
Public Key Cryptography standard number
RKCS1。那么我已经几次告诉大家，永远不要使用
one PKCS one. So I've already told you a
couple of times that you should never use
所谓的教科书RSA。大家永远不应该直接使用RSA
what's called textbook RSA. You should
never directly encrypt the message using
因为这是不安全的。大家在应用RSA函数前
RSA because that's insecure. You always
have to do something to the message before
必须始终对明文做些处理。我们上节看过了ISO的标准
you actually apply the RSA function. We
saw the ISO standard in the previous
我们生成了一个随机x，用RSA加密x
segment where what we did is we generated
a random x, encrypted x using RSA, and
然后从这个x，我们推出一个对称加密密钥。不过
then from this x we derived a symmetric
encryption key. But that's actually not how
这还不是RSA在实际中的应用。在实际中，事情不太一样
RSA is used in practice. In practice
things worked a little differently and
实际中，系统生成一个对称加密密钥
typically what happens is the system
generates a symmetric encryption key and
然后让RSA去加密这个给定的对称加密密钥
then RSA is asked to encrypt the given
symmetric encryption key rather than
而不是生成对称密钥，作为RSA加密的一部分。那么在实际中
generating the symmetric key as part of
RSA encryption. So in practice as I
如我所说，RSA系统有一个输入的对称密钥需要加密
say, what happens the RSA system is given
this input a symmetric encryption key to
例如，这个可能是一个AES密钥，128位
encrypt for example this could be a, an AES
key that would be like 128 bits and then
然后这个密钥被加密，首先我们取这128位
the way this key is actually encrypted is
first we take these 128 bits and we expand
我们把它们扩展成整个模的大小。例如，这个模是2048位
them into the full modulo size. For
example, this would be 2048 bits, and then
然后我们应用RSA函数。那么问题是，这是怎样预处理的？
we apply the RSA function. And so the
question is, how should this preprocessing
我们应该如何把给我们的128位AES密钥扩展成2048位
be done? How should we expand the 128 bit
AES key that was given to us into a 2048
然后再应用RSA呢？进一步的问题是
bit value that can then be applied with
RSA? And then furthermore the question is,
我们如何论证得到的系统是安全的呢？
how do we argue that the resulting system
is secure? So in all the way of doing it
在实际中这是广泛应用的，即所谓的PKCS1 1.5
which is actually very widely deployed in
practice is what's called PKCS1 version
公钥密码学标准，也就是PKCS的意思
1.5, Public Key Cryptography Standard,
that's what PKCS stands for. So I wanna
那么我想给大家展示这个机制是如何工作的，
特别地，我会给大家看所谓的
show you how this mechanism works and in
particular, I'll show you what's called
PKCS1模式2。模式2表示加密，模式1表示签名
PKCS1 Mode 2. Mode 2 denotes
encryption, mode 1 denotes signatures so
那么这里我们只看加密。PKCS1工作的过程如下
here we're gonna just focus on the
encryption. So the way PKCS1 works is
你取你的明文，比如说这里是128位AES密钥
as follows, you take your message, this
would be the 128 bit AES key for example,
把它放在你要产生的值的最低128位
and you put it as the least significant bits
of the value that you're creating. The
接下来你在它后面附上16个1，即十六进制的FF
next thing you do is you append sixteen
bits of one to it, you know FF.
这是16个1。然后接下来把它附在这个随机密码本的后面
This is sixteen bits of one. And then the
next you do is you append the random pad
这个密码本中任何地方都不含FF
that actually does not contain FF
anywhere inside the random pad. So this
这个密码本类似于1900位随机数
is basically something like on the order
of what is it, 1900 random bits except
但这个随机数里面不含FF。最后在结果的最高位
that there are on FF's inside those random
bits and finally at the very top, you put
放上数02。这意味着这个明文已经被PKCS1模式2编码了
the number 02. This indicates that this
plain text has been encoded using PKCS1
那么这整个值，我们刚刚创建的整个值
mode 2. And then this whole value here,
this whole thing that we just created.
这就是一个2048位的字符串，作为RSA函数的输入
This is just 2048 bit string is the thing
that gets fed into the RSA function and is
去计算它的e次方模N，得到的就是PKCS1的密文
raised to the power of e modulo N. And the
resulting thing is PKCS1 ciphertext. Now
现在当然，解密者要求RSA函数的逆，还原这个分组
the decrypter of course is going to invert
the RSA function, He's gonna get back this
他会看最高位
block, He's gonna look at the most
significant bits and he's gonna say
发现是02，意味着这是PKCS1格式的
there's a 02 in there that means that this
PKCS one formatted. Since it's PKCS one
它会移除这些02，它会移除所有的这些随机密码本
formatted, it's gonna remove those 02.
It's gonna remove all the random pad up
直到遇见FF，然后剩下的就是最初明文
until the FF. And then anything
that stays beyond that is the original
然后用这个明文来解密密文的内容
message which is then used you know to say
decrypt the actual body of the ciphertext.
如我所说，这个机制应用极广，例如
And as I said, this mechanism is extremely
widely deployed, For example, it's used in
HTTPS中就有用。现在有趣的是，这个PKCS1 1.5
是在上世纪80年代设计的
HTTPS. Now interestingly, this PKCS1
version 1.5 was designed in the late 80's.
当时还没有安全性证明可以论证这个机制事实上是安全的
There was really no security proof to
argue that this mechanism is in fact
事实上，这是一种很普遍的现象：在没有安全性证明的情况下
secure. And as it turns out, it is very
common when there is no security proof, it
实际上系统会被破解，这里有一个非常优雅的攻击
turns out that actually things break and
there's a very, very elegant attack due to
由Bleichenbacher在1998年提出，
Daniel Bleichenbacher展示了如何攻击
Bleichenbacher back in 1998, Daniel
Bleichenbacher which shows how to attack
PKCS1，当他被使用在HTTPS中时。那么我们看
这个攻击是怎样工作的
PKCS1 when it's used for example inside of
HTTPS. So let's see how the attack works.
其想法是，假设攻击者截获了一个特定密文
So the idea is this, supposed the attacker
intercepted a certain ciphertext so this
那么这是PKCS1密文，那么要点是，它是用PKCS1编码的
is PKCS1 ciphertext so the point is
it's encoded using PKCS1 and then the
然后结果作为RSA函数的输入。我们把这个密文叫做
result is fed into the RSA function. And
we call the ciphertext the output of the
RSA函数的输出。攻击者想解密密文
RSA function. The attacker wants to
basically decrypt the ciphertext, So let
让我给大家抽象地展示攻击者会怎么做。我们先简化SSL
me show you abstractly what the attacker
is gonna do. We're gonna just simplify SSL
比如说攻击者可以直接发送密文给网页服务器
and just say that the attacker can
basically send the ciphertext directly to
服务器将试图使用它的私钥去解密密文
the web server. The web server is gonna
try and decrypt the ciphertext using its
它怎么办呢？在解密之后，首先
secret key. And then what is it gonna do?
Well, the first thing it does after the
它问：密文的解密结果是否是PKCS1编码的？
decryption, well, it's gonna ask: is the
decryption of the ciphertext PKCS1
换句话说，它会看最高几位并问
encoded? In other words, it's gonna look
at the most significant bits and ask: is
最高两位是02吗？如果是，才继续正常的解密
this 02 in the most significant positions? If
they are, it's gonna continue properly
然后继续执行协议；如果这些最高位不是02
decrypting and then continue with the
protocol and if there is no 02 in those
就会声明一个错误。那么如果明文最高位是02
positions, it's gonna announce an error.
So if the most significant bits of the
就会如期执行协议
plaintext are 02, it's gonna continue
with the protocol as expected, if the most
如果最高位不是02，就会返回一个错误
significant bits are not 02 is gonna send
back an error message and tell the
告诉攻击者，你发送了一条无效的密文。
现在令人惊奇的是
attacker, hey, you sent in invalid
ciphertext. Now the amazing thing is that,
这一点让攻击者得以测试出，给定密文的最高16位
this lets the attacker test whether the
sixteen most significant bits of the
是否为02。换句话说，攻击者可以提交
decryption of the given ciphertext are 02
or not. In other words, the attacker can
他想提交给网页服务器的任何密文，网页服务器
submit whatever ciphertext he wants to the
web server. The web server will invert the
都会求RSA函数的逆，然后告诉攻击者逆的结果是否以02开头
RSA function and then tell the attacker
whether the inversion started with 02 or
那么某种意义上，这就给了攻击者一个神谕，使得他可以测试
not. So in some sense gives the attacker an
oracle that lets him test whether the
任意密文的逆是否以02开头。实际上
inversion of any ciphertext begins with 02
or not. And it turns out that's actually
这足以完全解密攻击者想解密的任何密文
enough to completely decrypt any
ciphertext the attacker wants, Just add
一点点的信息泄漏，因为RSA的特性
little bit of information leakage just by
properties of RSA let the attacker
让攻击者完全解密一个给定密文。那么攻击者会这么干
completely decrypt a given ciphertext.
Also here's what the attacker is gonna do,
他有一个他想解密的密文
well, he has a ciphertext that he wants to
decrypt so what he'll do is he'll take a
当然他把密文直接交给网页服务器
cyphertext and of course feed that
directly into the web server and ask does
询问它是否以02开头。接下来
it begin with the 02 or not. The next
thing he's gonna do is he's gonna choose a
攻击者选择一个随机值r，他要构建一个新密文c'
random value r and he's gonna build a new
ciphertext c prime. Which is (r to the e)
也就是(r^e)c mod N。这会造成什么？
如果我们把r带入RSA函数
c modulo N. Now what does that do? If we
pull the r into the RSA function, really
我们只是与RSA明文相乘，PKCS1封装的明文m
what we just did is we multiply the RSA
plaintext, you know the PKCS1 including
我们用r去乘它，计算整项的e次方
in m, we multiply that by r and that,
that whole thing gets raised to the power
好，那么这就是c乘(r^e)的效果
of e. Okay. So that's the effect of
multiplying c by (r to the e). It multiplies
它把r与明文相乘，r是攻击者控制的值
the plaintext by r, a value that the
attacker controls. And then he's gonna
然后攻击者会把c'发送给网页服务器，服务器的回答是肯定的
send c prime to the web server and the web
server is gonna say yes, this starts with
以02开头，或是否定的，不以02开头。那么现在
我们可以把这个问题进行抽象
02 or no, this doesn't start with 02. So
now we can abstract this problem to
推广到更一般的情况，大家可以考虑如下情形
something more general which you can think
of as the following so I have this number
我知道这个数x，这个数是我想获得的PKCS1对m的编码
x in my head. This is the number I'm
trying to get The PKCS1 encoding on m. I'm
我考虑这个数x，然后我让你选择r
thinking of this number x and then what I
let you do is for r, which way r of your
我会告诉你r*x mod n是否以02开头
choice I will tell you whether r times x mod n
starts with 02 or not. And it turns out by
实际上通过询问足够多的这样的问题，比如问数百万次
asking enough questions it turns out
either by million questions of this type,
你就可以还原x的全部了。只通过学习r*x是否以02开头
you can basically recover all of x. Just
by learning whether r times x begins with 02
只通过问足够多这样的问题，实际上你可以还原x
or not by asking enough questions, you can
actually recover x. So in reality what
实际上这意味着攻击者可以抓取一个给定的密文
this means is that the attacker can
capture a given ciphertext. This maybe
这个可能对应一个密文，比如用户输入的信用卡号
corresponds to a ciphertext where the user
enters the credit card number or a
或密码，现在攻击者想解密密文
password, and now the attacker wants to
decrypt the ciphertext. What he would do
他会发送一百万条像这样的密文
is he would send about a million
ciphertext like this, the web server for
对每条这样的密文，网页服务器会回复这个明文是否以02开头
each ciphertext is gonna respond whether
the plaintext begins with 02 or not and at
在攻击的最后，攻击者给出密文c的解密结果
the end of the attack, the attacker just
blocks away with the, decryption of the
这对大家来说可能有点神奇
ciphertext c. So this might seem a
little magical to you, how are you able to
怎么能够只通过学习明文的最高位是否是02
just from learning whether the most
significant bits are 02 or not, how you're
就能还原整个明文呢？那么我来给大家一个简单的例子
able to recover the entire plain text. So
let me show you a simple example of this.
我叫这个例子为幼儿Bleichenbacher，只求表达
I'll call those baby Bleichenbacher just
to kinda get the idea across on how this
这个攻击的基本想法。那么设想攻击者可以发送密文c
attack might work. So imagine that the
attacker is able to send the ciphertext c,
网页服务器会用私钥解密，不过我们假设
the web server is gonna use the secret key
to decrypt but let's suppose that instead
服务器不检查开头是否是02，而是看最高位
of checking for 02 or not, all the web
server does is he asked is the most
是否为1。如果最高位是1，网页服务器会说：是
significant bit one or not. If the most
significant bit is one, the web server
如果最高位不是1，网页服务器会返回"不"
says yes. If the most significant bit is
not one, the web server is no. Moreover,
为求进一步简化，我们假设RSA的模N是2的某次幂
to simplify things, let's assume that the
RSA module is n is a power of two. So n =
即N=2^n。当然，这不是一个有效的RSA模
two^n. Of course, this is not a valid RSA
modulus. An RSA modulus used to be a
RSA模是一个两指数的乘积。但为求简便
product of two distinct primes. But again,
just to keep things simple, let's pretend
我们假定N是2的幂。那么现在大家发现
for a second that n is actually a power of
two. So now you realize that by sending
通过给网页服务器发送密文c，攻击者只是
the ciphertext c over to the web server,
the adversary just learn the most
学习明文x的最高位。服务器的行为
significant bits of the plaintext x.
Basically, the server's behavior completely
完全泄漏了最高位是什么。现在攻击者可以
reveals what the most significant is. Now
what the attacker can do is he can
把密文乘以2^e。现在乘以2^e
multiply the ciphertext by two to the e.
Now multiplying by two to the e has the
就有去乘明文x的效果，就是把x乘以2
effect of multiplying the plaintext x. By
two simply multiplying x by two and
因为我们是工作在2的n次方模下，乘以2就意味着左移
because we're working mod two to the N,
multiplying by two basically means shift
好。那么现在当我们左移时，事实上我们学到了
left, okay. So now when we shift left in
fact we get to learn the most significant
2x的最高位，也就等于学到了x的次高位，好的
bits of 2x which is really the second most
significant bit of x, okay. So, again the
2x的最高位，我们左移了x，并取模N
most significant bit of 2x basically we
shift x to the left. And we reduce modulo
那么现在，2x mod N的最高位
n. So now, the most significant bit of 2x
modulo n is basically the second most
也就是x的次高位。那么我们就学到了x的另一位内容
significant bit of x. So now we learned
another bit of x. And now we're gonna
现在我们重复这步，询问c=4^e
repeat this again. We're gonna query a
four to the e c, That corresponds to
这对应于4x的e次方。询问4x会得到
querying of 4x to the power e. Querying of
4x basically reveals the most significant
4x mod N的最高位。4对应着左移两位
bit of 4x mod n. 4x four corresponds the
shifting by two bits. Which mean now we
意味着现在我们学到了x的第三高位。当我们一次次重复这些
get to learn the third most significant
bit of x. And when we repeat this again,
对于不同的c的倍数，大家可以看出
and again, and again for different multiples
of c and you can see that after just a
经过一些询问，大约1000到2000次询问，我们就还原了x
few queries, about a 1,000 or 2,000
queries, we'll recover all of x. The
Bleichenbacher需要一百万次的原因在于
reason Bleichenbacher needed about a
million queries is because he wasn't
他不是测试一位，他是在测试最高两位是否为02
testing for one, He was actually testing
for 02 or not 02 and that basically means
这意味着他需要上百万次询问，而不是2000次
that he needs instead of 2,000 queries he
needs actually a million queries but
但那足以还原所有的明文了
that's still enough to recover all of the
plaintext text. Okay? So I hope this
那么我希望这解释了为什么这个攻击是可能的。
为什么关于RSA逆的最高位的一点点信息
explains why this attack is possible. Why
just this little bit of information about
就足以完全解密RSA了
the most significant bits of the RSA
inverse is enough to completely decrypt
至少可以说，PKCS1在网页服务器上曾如上述所实现
RSA. So the bottom line here is that PKCS1 as implemented in web server as up
直到这种攻击被发现，它变得不安全了
until this attack was discovered was
basically insecure because the attacker
因为攻击者可以解密他想要的密文，
通过向网页服务器提交足够都的询问即可
could essentially decrypt a ciphertext he
wants just by issuing enough queries to
那么我们如何抵抗这一攻击呢？
the web server. So how do we defend
against this attack? Well, so the SSL
SSL社区想通过对代码的最小改动
community basically wanted the minimum
change in their code that would prevent
就可以阻止这种攻击。如果大家看RFC，
他们提出的方案如下
this attack from working and so if you
look at the RFC, what they propose is the
这里有很多内容，但他们提出的大致上是说
following. Well, there's a lot of text
here but basically what they propose is to
如果在你应用RSA解密之后，你会获得一个明文
say that if after you apply the RSA
decryption, you get a plaintext that's not
它并不是PKCS1编码的。换句话说，它不是以02开头的
PKCS1 encoded. In other words it doesn't
start with 02. What you're supposed to do
你可以选取某个随机字符串r。只假定
is basically choose some random string r.
And just pretend that the plaintext is
明文是一个随机字符串r，只当什么也没发生
just a random string r and continuous as
nothing happened and of course the
当然稍后协议会失败。具体地说，如果PKCS1编码不正确
protocol will fail later on. So to be
concrete you see if the PKCS one encoding
你会说预备主密钥
is not correct, what you would do is you
would just say the premaster secret is
是这个随机字符串，或只是随机接收的，我们继续协议
this random string or that we just picked
up off thin air and let's continue the
当然建立会话会失败，因为客户端和服务端
protocol and of course the session set up
will fail because the client and the
最终达成的交换密钥不一致，这会导致会话终止
server will end up agreeing on different
keys and that will cause the session to
我们实际上不告诉攻击者明文是否以02开头
terminate. So we actually don't tell the
attacker whether the plaintext begins with
我们只是假定明文是某个随机值
02 or not. All we do is just pretend that
the plaintext is some random value. So
那么对于许多网页服务器来说，这只是一点点的代码改动
this was a minor code change to many web
servers and it was fairly easy to get
是容易布置的，事实上时至今日，大多数的网页服务器
deployed and in fact most web servers out
there today implement this version of
已经实现了这一版本的PKCS1。但是这带来了问题
PKCS1. However, this kind of raises the
question of whether PKCS1 should be
PKCS1是否应该都被改变，使得我们得以证明选择密文安全性
changed all together so that we actually
are able to prove chosen ciphertext
这让我们以一种不同的方法来进行使用RSA的加密
security. And that brings us to a
different way of doing encryption using
即所谓的优化非对称加密补齐OAEP
RSA which is called Optimal Asymmetric
Encryption Padding, OAEP. And in fact the
事实上这个PKCS标准被更新了，而PKCS版本2实际上支持OAEP
PKCS standard was updated and PKCS1 version
2.0 actually has support for OAEP which is
而OAEP是更好的使用RSA加密的方法。
那么让我解释下OAEP是如何工作的
a better way of doing RSA encryption. So
let me explain how OAEP works. So OAEP is
那么OAEP是由Bellare和Rogaway于1994年提出的。OAEP如下工作
due to the Bellare and Rogaway back in 1994. And
the way OAEP works is as follows. So you
取你想加密的明文信息，例如128位的AES密钥
take your message that you wanna encrypt
this for example could be the 128 bits AES
然后首先在明文后面附上一小段密码本
key. And then the first thing you do is
you append a short pad to it. So in this
在这里，你在前面附上01，然后再加一组0
case, you put a 01 in the beginning and
then you add a whole bunch of zeroes. How
根据标准来定要加多少0
many zeroes is actually depends on the
standard but you know that's supposed like
假设这里有128位0。然后大家也选择一个随机值
they're 128 zeroes in here. And then you
also choose a random value so that this
使得这整个字符串与你的RSA模一样大，比如说2047位
whole string is as big as your RSA modulus
so let's just say this is 2047 bits. Now
现在在你应用RSA函数之前，首先取你选的随机数
before you apply the RSA function, you
first of all take the random value that
把它交给哈希函数，这个哈希函数产生一个值
you chose and you feed it into the hash
function. This hash function produces a
这个值与你编码的左边一样大。你把输出求异或
value that's as big as the left hand side
of your encoding. You XOR the outputs.
把得到的结果交给另一个哈希函数，我们叫它g
You feed the result into another hash
function which we call a g. You XOR
你用一个随机值去异或，最后会得到两个值
that with a random value. And then
finally, you get these two values that you
你把它们联结起来，好。你把左右相联结
concatenate together. Okay, So, you
concatenate either left side and the
得到2047位长的字符串，这也就是
right side that gives you something that
says is 2047 bits long and that's the thing
你应用RSA函数的字符串。结果就是RSA加密
that you apply the RSA function to. And the
result is the RSA encryption. Now there's
现在有一个2001年证明的理论，由藤崎英一郎、
本明、Pointcheval和Stern提出
a theory that was proved in 2001, due to
Fujisaki, Okamoto, Pointcheval, and Stern,
证明了事实上如果你只假设RSA函数是陷门函数
that shows that in fact if all you do is
you, you assume that the RSA function is a
是一个安全的陷门函数，但事实上这个模式
Trapdoor permutation, a secure Trapdoor
permut ation, but in fact this mode of
使用RSA加密是选择密文安全的话，我们还必须假设
encrypting using RSA is in fact chosen
ciphertext secure but we have to
函数h和g是某种理想的哈希函数才行，如我所说
assume that the functions h and g are kind
of ideal hash functions as I said these
这些叫做随机神谕。我们假设h和g是随机函数
are called random oracles. Basically, we
assume that h and g are just random
从它们的定义域映射到它们的值域。当然在实际中
functions from their domains to their
range. In practice of course when OAEP is
当实现OAEP时，对于h和g，人们就使用SHA-256
implemented, people just use SHA-256
say for h and g. Why is this called
那为什么这叫做优化非对称加密补齐呢？
为什么要说优化呢？
Optimal Asymmetric Encryption Padding?
Why is this o? Why does this stands for
原因在于，如果你看密文，会注意到
optimal? Well, the reason is if you look
at the ciphertext, you'll notice that the
其密文是尽可能短的。密文与RSA输出一样长
ciphertext is basically as short as it can
be. The ciphertext is exactly the length
没有附在密文后面的值
of one RSA output, there are no trailing
values that are appended to the ciphertext
例如ISO标准中，如果大家记得，即使你必须加密
whereas for example, the ISO standard
if you remember even if you had to encrypt
一个非常短的明文，你必须使用RSA加密x
a very short message, what you would have
to do is you would have to encrypt x using
然后在x后面附上使用对称加密系统加密的短消息
RSA and then append to that x, the
encryption with the short message under
即使你必须加密128位AES密钥
the symmetric encryption system. So even
if you have just to encrypt a 128 bit AES
根据ISO标准，你会获得一个RSA输出加上一段对称密码
key, with the ISO standard you would
get one RSA output plus a symmetric
而在OAEP中，你只获得了一个RSA输出，没有其他东西
cipher whereas with OAEP, you just get one
RSA output and nothing else so in that
那么从某种意义上，这是优化的，密文长度是优化的
sense, it's optimal, Optimal in terms of
the length of the ciphertext.
有趣的是，这个定理依赖于RSA的性质。事实上
Interestingly, this theorem here really
rely on properties of RSA. And in fact,
如果你使用一个普通的陷门置换，那么这个定理不成立
the theorem is known to be false if
you use a general trapdoor permutation.
其他的置换未必具备RSA的代数性质
Some other permutation doesn't have the
algebraic properties of RSA. So that left
剩下的问题是，如果我们有一个普通陷门置换
this question of if we have a general
trapdoor permutation, what is the correct
如何正确地使用OAEP呢？实际上，对OAEP有一个小修改
way to do OAEP? And it turns out, there's
a minor modification to OAEP which makes
可以使得结果更为一般。这是Shoup于2001年给出的结果
the result more general. This is a result
due to Shoup back in 2001. Just shows that
证明了如果给我一个普通陷门置换f，实际上
if you give me a general trapdoor
permutation f. It turns out if you replace
如果不用OAEP里的固定补齐，而是使用这个哈希函数w
the fixed pad that's using OAEP by a hash
function, this hash function w, which
它是你要加密的明文m和随机性r的哈希函数
happens to be a hash function of the
message m and the randomness r that
然后在解密时，检测这个哈希函数的值是否正确
you're encrypting with, and then during
decryption, you actually check that this
那么当你解密时，检查w(mr)
hash function value is correct. So when
you decrypt, you actually check the w of
是否与明文中这个位置的内容一致
mr is really what's written in this
position in the plaintext. If you do that
这种改进后的OAEP叫做OAEP+。事实上它是CCA安全的
then basically this OAEP called OAEP+.
Is in fact CCS secure, Chosen Ciphertext
对任意陷门置换都是选择密文安全的，不必依赖于
Secure for any trapdoor permutation. You
don't have to rely on a specific
RSA的特定性质。还有一个结果叫做简单非对称加密补齐
properties of RSA. There's another result
called Simple Asymmetric Encryption
SAEP+，就是说如果要依赖RSA的性质
Padding, SAEP+ which basically says
that if you are gonna rely on properties
那么在特殊情况下，当RSA的公钥指数等于3时
of RSA, then in particular way with RSA
when the public exponent is equal to
实际上你不需要第二阶段的加密工作
3, it turns out you actually don't
need the second stage of encryption. The
这里这个简单的补齐机制使用了函数w
simple padding scheme here again using the
function w is actually already enough to
就足以保证选择密文安全了。那么这些是OAEP的变种
guarantee chosen ciphertext security. So
these are variants OAEP but they're not
但它们并没有被实际使用。我只想提一下，
让大家知道它们的存在
really used. I just wanted to mention and
to let you know they exist. These are not
这些没被使用，而被使用的OAEP已被标准化了
really used mainly OAEP has been
standardized is what's used. Although
尽管在实际中，RSA在公钥加密中的最一般的应用
again in reality, the most common
application of RSA for public encryption
实际上就是这个被标准化的PKCS1，在HTTPS的RFC中
is in fact this PKCS1 that's
standardized in the HTTPS RFC. So just to
为了确保大家理解清楚这个解密是如何工作的，我问大家
make sure it is clear in your mind how
decryption actually works, let me ask you,
如何解密SAEP密文ct。这里你有密文ct
how would you decrypt an SAEP ciphertext
ct. So here, you're given the ciphertext
问题是下面三种方法中，哪种是正确的密文解密？
ct here and the question is which of these
three methods is the correct way of
那么正确答案是第一个，我们来看为什么
decrypting the ciphertext. So the correct
answer is the first one and let's see why.
有了密文，我们首先需要应用RSA逆函数
Well, given the ciphertext the first thing
what we need to do is apply the RSA
作用于密文，我们会得到RSA明文
inverse functions, the ciphertext and that
will give us the RSA plaintext which
正好就是x和r。那么我们得到了这里的x和r
happens to be in this case x and r. So we
get this x and r here. The next thing we
接下来我们需要使用函数h计算r的哈希值，然后把结果与x异或
need to do is we need to hash r using the
function h and XOR the result with x and
这会给我们m和w(m,r)。最后我们需要确保
that will give us m and wm, r. And the
last we need to do is to make sure that
补齐W(m,r)是正确的，这样我们检查w是否等于W(m,r)
the pad W(m,r) is correct so we check that
in fact w is equal to W(m,r) and if so we
如果是，我们输出m；如果不是，我们输出⊥，表示密文无效
output m and if not, we output bottom to
say that the ciphertext is invalid and
因此解密算法拒绝了它。顺便说下，我想强调
the decryption algorithm rejects it. And
by the way I'd like to emphasize that this
解密中的这个补齐检查在我们看过的所有的机制中都是很重要的
checking of the pad during decryption is
crucial in all of the schemes that we
例如OAEP+和SAEP+，就是这样解密的
just saw. So for example, in both OAEP+ and SAEP+, it's doing decryption.
检查补齐是否正确是很重要的
It's very important to check that the pad
is in fact correct so that the value of w
这样解密时，你在这里得到的w值就是哈希值W(m,r)
that you get here during the encryption
really is the hash under the capital W of
类似地在OAEP中，在解密时，这个检查也很重要
m and r and similarly on OAEP, it's very
important to check it during decryption.
事实上这个补齐值是个常数010000000
In fact, the value of the pad is the
constant 010000000. And of course if it
当然如果它不是01000，你就输出⊥，说密文是无效的
happens to be not 01000 then you output
bottom and you say the ciphertext is
我想指出的最后一点是，实际上实现OAEP
invalid. The last thing I wanna point out
is that actually implementing OAEP can be
可能是很困难的，我们来看为什么。
假设你写了一个OAEP解密程序
quite tricky and let's see why. So
supposed you have, you write an OAEP
取密文为输入，首先
decryption routine that takes the
ciphertext as input. The first thing you
对密文应用RSA逆函数
would do is you would apply the RSA
inverse function to the ciphertext and you
比如说你希望得到n位值输出，2047位
would say well, you expect to get an n bit
value out, you know 2047 bits in the case
在2048位RSA模的情形下。如果你获得了某个
of 2048 bit RSA modulus and if you get
something that's bigger than two to the
比2^2047大的数，你就拒绝。我们说错误=1，然后离开
2047, you say reject. We say error = one
and we go to Exit. The next thing we're
接下来我们检查补齐是否是正确的
gonna do is we're gonna check whether the
pad is in fact the correct pad and again
如果补齐不正确，我们还是拒绝和离开
if the pad is not the correct pad, then
again, we're gonna reject and go to Exit.
这个实现的问题是，我希望大家已经猜到了
The problem with this implementation is
well by now I hope you kind of guessed it
这对于计时攻击来说是脆弱的
is it's vulnerable to a timing attack,
right. So essentially by leaking timing
通过泄漏时间信息，攻击者可以解出是什么导致了错误
information the attacker can now figure
out what caused the error. Was it, that
是RSA解密后数太大的错误
was there an error the RSA decryption
happened to be too big or was there an
还是因为补齐太大的错误？如果攻击者
error because the pad happened to be too
large? And if the attacker can this
通过计时可以区分这两种错误。那么与Bleichenbacher类似
distinguish these two errors say by
timing. Then it turns out similar to the
实际上是可能完全解密任何你选择的密文的
Bleichenbacher attack, it's possible to
completely decrypt any ciphertext of your
一丁点的信息泄漏
choice. Just at very, very, very small
leak of information would completely allow
都可以让攻击者完全解密任何他想要的密文
the attacker to decrypt completely any
ciphertext that he wants to. So this shows
这展示了，即使你正确地实现了OAEP的数学部分
that if you, even if you implement the
mathematics of OAEP decryption correctly,
你也可能会搞砸，是自己暴露于计时攻击中
you can very easily mess up and open
yourself up to a timing attack which would
这会使得你的实现是完全不安全的。通常的教训是
make your implementation completely
insecure. So as usual, the lesson is,
不要自己去实现密码学，特别是RSA、OAEP
don't implement crypto yourself in
particular, RSA OAEP is particularly
自己去实现将是非常危险的。就使用标准库即可
dangerous to implement yourself. Just use one
of the standard libraries for example,
例如OpenSSL有一个OAEP实现，当然他们做得非常小心
OpenSSL has an OAEP implementation and of
course what they do is very careful to
确保OAEP解密的运行时间总是相同的
make sure that the running time of OAEP
decrypt is always the same no matter what
无论发送什么错误。好，那么我们就说到这
causes the error. Okay, So let's stop here
and then in the next segment we'll talk
下节我们讨论RSA陷门置换的安全性
about the security of the RSA trapdoor
permutation.